בוקר טוב, Boker tov, so good, good day of שיעור, Shiur, second
day of חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. We pick up on דף כ"א,
Daf Kaf Aleph, 21, and we are talking about how we know
which things are included in the איסור דם issur dam and eventually
we're also going to get to a distinction between life blood and
other blood which is a question about whether you get כרת kares
or it's a straight negative prohibition. But right now we're just discussing
which things are completely excluded and the Torah mentions עוף ובהמה, oph
ve'behemah, bird and animal, and based on that we sort of pointed
out some distinguishing characteristics about heavy טומאה, tumah, light טומאה, tumah, meat,
and so on and we'll go through each one in a minute
and thereby we excluded things like fish and grasshoppers and humans which
are here being referred to as bipeds etc. So let's take a
look now at the גמרא, Gemara, five lines from the top,
I'm sorry, three lines from the top. לעוף ולבהמה. L'oph v'labehemah. So
now we are once again looking at the פסוק pasuk and the
phrase לעוף ולבהמה, l'oph v'labehemah, birds and large animals or whatever,
mammals. אימא, Ima, why don't we make the following, why if we
just had those two words we could have, why we would have
read if we or rather if we just had one of the
words we would have read the פסוק pasuk the following way. Let's
say we just had the word לעוף. l'oph. So I would have
said, אימא עוף שאין בו כלאיים אף בהמה שאין בו כלאיים, ima
oph she'ein bo kilayim, aph behemah she'ein bo kilayim, maybe the same
way there's no כלאיים kilayim by birds, only animals you only have
an איסור דם issur dam by animals that have no כלאיים. kilayim.
So that's what I would have said if it just said the
word לעוף. l'oph. תלמוד לומר ולבהמה. Talmud lomar l'behemah. Therefore it had
to say ולבהמה. l'behemah. So here's the question is why couldn't it
have just said either לעוף l'oph or ולבהמה? l'behemah? Why did it
have to say both? And the answer is because if it would
have just said one I would have defined the field too narrowly.
Now what's the idea of there's no כלאיים kilayim by birds? I
mean the גמרא Gemara will explain all this but I'll just tell
you right now, I mean there is an איסור issur to crossbreed
birds, so the issue is that it means that there's no
כלאיים kilayim by the material, the threads that you can produce from
birds, right? So you can make כלאיים kilayim from sheep, from wool,
but you can't make כלאיים kilayim from any of from bird feathers.
So therefore maybe I would have only applied it to cows and
goats but I wouldn't have applied it to sheep where they can
produce a material of כלאיים. kilayim. So therefore it had to say
ולבהמה. l'behemah. אימא בהמה שאינה באם על הבנים, Ima behemah she'eina b'eima
labanim, had it just said בהמה, behemah, I would have
said only it's only בהמות behemas because there's not the prohibition of
taking you know the mother and the child.
Now excuse me or let me rephrase that. It's only with animals
that do not have the prohibition of taking mother and the child.
What birds
do not have the prohibition of
באם על הבנים? eima labanim? Which would be non-kosher birds, non-kosher birds
or would have been let's say birds that are מזומן mezuman that
are not you don't just chance upon, right? לא תקח האם על
הבנים. Lo sikach ha'eima al habanim. Now by the way it is
interesting because by animals you do have the prohibition of אותו ואת
בנו לא תשחטו ביום אחד oto ve'es beno lo sishchatu beyom echad
but they don't have the prohibition of actually taking together. So therefore
maybe I would have if I would have just said בהמה behemah
I would have maybe focused on that criteria why that should at
all be relevant to the איסור דם issur dam who knows but
okay. So therefore and I would have excluded non-kosher birds,
I'm sorry and I should I would have only limited it to
non-kosher birds I would not have applied it to kosher birds that
have that prohibition of באם על הבנים. eima labanim. תלמוד לומר לעוף
ולבהמה. Talmud lomar l'oph v'labehemah. So therefore it had to say both.
Okay so that's just telling me even though I've made all the
other distinguishing characteristics I said before to exclude things like grasshoppers and
so on and fish, it still needed to say both birds and
בהמה behemah or otherwise I would have defined the field too narrowly.
Okay so now the גמרא Gemara says ואימא כל דם כלל. v'eima
kol dam klall. So okay that's the end of the ברייתא. Baraita.
Now why didn't I say do the following דרשה? drasha? It says
it says the פסוק pasuk says וכל דם לא תאכלו
בכל מושבתיכם.
v'chol dam lo socheilu bechol
moshvoseichem. Okay so why don't we say כל דם kol dam is
a
כלל, klall, לעוף ולבהמה l'oph v'labehemah פרט, prat, and then it says
לעוף ולבהמה l'oph v'labehemah that's a פרט. prat. כלל ופרט אין בכלל
אלא מה שבפרט. Klall u'prat ein b'klall ela mah she'b'prat. How do
we say anything similar to עוף ובהמה? oph v'behemah? Why don't I
just say just עוף בהמה? oph behemah? It's a כלל klall and
a פרט prat and therefore it would not go beyond עוף ובהמה.
oph v'behemah.
What does it go beyond?
Well ah so the question is what is not an עוף oph
and not a בהמה behemah that is an איסור דם? issur dam?
Now you can't say חיה chayah because we're going to assume חיה
chayah is בכלל בהמה. be'klall behemah. So we'll see that in a
minute. The גמרא Gemara will tell you. But let's proceed the answer
okay. So the question is maybe I should have just said just
עוף ובהמה oph v'behemah not expanded it at all. So the גמרא
Gemara says עוף ובהמה אין מידי אחריני
לא, oph v'behemah in midi achrini lo, just עוף ובהמה oph v'behemah
nothing else. So it says נפש אשר תאכל כל דם. nefesh asher
tochal kol dam. The next פסוק pasuk says if anybody eats any
blood which is more inclusive. Now that ends ונכרתה הנפש ההיא מעמיה.
v'nichresah hanefesh hahi me'ameha.
Okay so that is you get כרת kares whoever eats any blood.
So that is another general statement, כלל. klall. So it says חזר
וכלל, chazar v'klall, that's another general statement. כלל ופרט וכלל אי אתה
דן אלא כעין הפרט. klal u-frat u-klal i atah dan ela ke-ein
ha-prat. So therefore it's similar to עוף ובהמה of u-vehemah but not
just עוף ובהמה of u-vehemah because there's another general statement that follows.
גמרא Gemara says one minute, והא לא דמי כללא בתרא לכללא קמא.
ve-ha lo dami klala batra le-klala kama. The second כלל klal is
not like the first כלל. klal. כללא קמא לאו כללא בתרא כרת.
klala kama lav klala batra kares. The first כלל klal is about
don't eat any blood, it's right? It's because וכל דם לא תאכלו.
ve-chol dam lo tochlu.
The second כלל klal is about getting כרת. kares. כל נפש אשר
תאכל כל דם, kol nefesh asher tochal kol dam, נפש אשר תאכל
כל דם.
nefesh asher
tochal kol dam.
It says כל דם kol dam but it's about the punishment of
כרת, kares, not about the prohibition. So who says you can combine
a כלל klal and a פרט prat that's about the prohibition with
a כלל klal that's about the punishment? Maybe they don't combine for
a כלל ופרט וכלל, klal u-frat u-klal, they're having they're talking about
different things. גמרא Gemara says no, האי תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל כללי
ופרטי דרשינן מן הדין גוונא. hai tanna devei rabbi yishmael klalei u-fratei
darshinan min hadein gavna.
This is רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael that makes a type of a
כלל ופרט klal u-frat like this. He makes a כלל ופרט וכלל,
klal u-frat u-klal, he's able to combine a פסוק pasuk that's about
a prohibition with a פסוק pasuk that is about a punishment. ואף
על גב דלא דמי כללא בתרא לכללא קמא, ve-af al gav de-lo
dami klala batra le-klala kama, even though the last one is not
so similar to the first one. Okay, so now we've explained why
we need to say both עוף ובהמה. of u-vehemah. We have a
כלל ופרט וכלל klal u-frat u-klal by combining the פסוק pasuk of
the prohibition with the פסוק pasuk of the punishment. And now we
focus in on the statement that says that why did I, you
know, that I, the גמרא's Gemara's question, which is if I didn't
have a כלל ופרט, klal u-frat, I would have just limited it,
כלל ופרט וכלל klal u-frat u-klal I would have just limited it
to עוף ובהמה. of u-vehemah. Well, isn't that what we're just limiting
it to? I mean, let's see. We excluded humans, we excluded fish,
we excluded grasshoppers, we excluded שרצים, shratzim, right? What did we not
exclude that isn't an עוף ובהמה? of u-vehemah? Right? At the end
of the day, it's just עוף ובהמה. of u-vehemah. So let's take
a look. Okay.
You know what, Michael? You got it. Exactly. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Where were
we? אמר
מר. amar mar. So כלל ופרט וכלל אי אתה דן אלא כעין
הפרט. klal u-frat u-klal i atah dan ela ke-ein ha-prat. מה הפרט
מפורש דבר שיש בו טומאה קלה וטומאה חמורה ויש בו איסור והיתר.
mah ha-prat meforash davar she-yesh bo tumah kalah ve-tumah chamurah ve-yesh bo
issur ve-heter. So we only go by things that are like עוף
ובהמה. of u-vehemah. What is it? They have both a light and
a heavy טומאה. tumah. They can both be an אב הטומאה av
ha-tumah and they can be food to receive טומאה. tumah. And there's
איסור והיתר, issur ve-heter, which means that, you know, it's אסור assur
unless you שחט shacht it, which will exclude things like grasshoppers and
fish. ויש בהן מין בשר, ve-yesh bahen min basar, the type of
a meat which excludes things like eggs. אף כל שיש בו טומאה
קלה וטומאה חמורה af kol she-yesh bo tumah kalah ve-tumah chamurah etc.
etc. אף כל דקתני לאתויי מאי? af kol de-katani le-atuyei mai? So
at the end of the day, what are we including? What at
the end of the day what are we including that's not a
bird and בהמה? behemah? And we're assuming חיה chayah is included in
בהמה. behemah. So at the end of the day, the only thing
that's אסור assur for דם dam is birds and בהמות behemos and
חיות. chayos. What else is included? And you can't say non-kosher, well,
non-kosher is also. The תורה Torah never said kosher בהמה behemah or
non-kosher בהמה behemah or whatever. So at the end of the day,
the תורה Torah told that there is an איסור issur for kosher
and non-kosher birds and בהמות behemos and חיות. chayos. So the גמרא
Gemara says, so Michael guessed it, אמר אבא בר אבין לאתויי דמו
של כוי. amar abba bar avin le-atuyei damo shel koy. Ah, to
include the blood of a כוי, koy, something that is indeterminate if
it's חיה chayah or בהמה, behemah, or maybe, and this is what
the גמרא Gemara here is going to say, it's a third species.
If it's just indeterminate, then you wouldn't need a פסוק, pasuk, right?
Because either it's a חיה chayah or a בהמה, behemah, and you're
חייב chayav for the blood of a חיה chayah or a בהמה.
behemah. So it wouldn't be, it wouldn't matter what category it's in,
it's immaterial. But here we're assuming that it's neither חיה chayah nor
בהמה, behemah, it's a species by itself. Okay? And therefore you need,
that's what you need this whole כלל ופרט וכלל klal u-frat u-klal
was according to the approach that a כוי koy was a species
in itself. So let's take a look.
מאי קסבר? mai kasavar? What did this תנא tanna hold? אי קסבר
כוי ספיקא הוא, ei kasavar koy sefeika hu, it's a question, is
it a חיה, chayah, is it בהמה, behemah, we just have no
way of knowing, but it's got to be one of them. איצטריך
קרא למיסר ספיקא? itztrich kra le-meisar sefeika? Who needs a פסוק pasuk
to forbid a doubt? Now, sometimes that פסוק pasuk means who needs
a פסוק pasuk to forbid a doubt,
it's forbidden anyway because it might be forbidden. But that's not what
it means here. Here it means it's definitely forbidden. Because since either
category is forbidden, whether חיה chayah or בהמה, behemah, who cares which
category it's in? It's really a moot point. Okay? Not it's אסור
assur because it's ספק. safek. It's moot. It's אסור assur whether it's
a חיה chayah or בהמה. behemah. So that would not be, you
would not need a general statement to include it. אלא קסבר כוי
בריה בפני עצמה הוא. ela kasavar koy biryah bifnei atzmah hu. It's
its own thing. It's neither a חיה chayah nor בהמה. behemah. And
therefore you need it to tell me that its blood is also
forbidden. So this whole big generic statement, which is very abstract ideas,
טומאה קלה, tumah kalah, טומאה חמורה, tumah chamurah, all those types of
things is just to include a כוי. koy. And if you held
that a כוי koy was either חיה chayah or בהמה, behemah, you
could have then at the end of the day it's just you
could have said כלל ופרט, klal u-frat, עוף ובהמה of u-vehemah end
of story. The only thing we're including that's not explicitly in the
פסוק pasuk is כוי koy assuming it's its own category. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אלא קסבר כוי בריה בפני
עצמה הוא. ela kasavar koy biryah bifnei atzmah hu. אשכחן דמו. ashkechan
damo. Now that you're going to say that it's completely a separate
thing, now the question is how are we going to know anything
about a כוי? koy? And so now you're telling me that the
blood is forbidden. חלבו מנלן? chelvo minalan? How do you know the
חלב chelev of
a
כוי koy is forbidden?
Right? If it' Not only that, it says don't eat the fat
of something that goes on the מזבח. mizbeach. A כוי koy doesn't
go on the מזבח. mizbeach. Okay, so let's see that. So how
do you know? I mean, that's the question obviously because we also
אסר asser חלב cheilev even of an animal... anyway, but we're moving
on. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: חלב מנלן? cheilev minalan?
מכל חלב. mikol cheilev. Okay, it says, it says you shall not
eat any fat. So since it says any, that includes even the
fat of a כוי. koy. The only thing that's excluded, it's not
again, it doesn't have to be a בהמה. behemah. It certainly doesn't
have to be something that just goes on the מזבח. mizbeach. As
long as it's not a חיה, chayah, the fat of anything that's
not a חיה, chayah, כל חלב kol cheilev includes it. So even
the fat of a כוי koy is forbidden. According to this approach,
I should say, by the way, that somebody who eats the fat
of a כוי koy is not עובר over a ספק איסור, safek
issur, he's doing a ודאי איסור. vadai issur. Right? Normally we assume
if you eat the fat of a כוי, koy, it's a ספק
איסור safek issur and you may, you know, that's an interesting question,
you could bring an אשם תלוי asham talui maybe if you don't
eat שתי חתיכות, shtei chatichot, you wouldn't bring a חטאת. chatat. But
here you would bring a definite חטאת chatat because it's its own
category and it's directly forbidden. Okay, so that's, that's that פסוק, pasuk,
כל חלב. kol cheilev. נבלתו מנלן? nevelato minalan? How do you know
the נבלה nevelah is forbidden if you didn't שחט shacht it? How
do you know you have to שחט shacht a כוי? koy? Maybe
it's its own third category, you don't have to שחט shacht it.
How do you know if you שחט shacht it, it's still forbidden?
If you don't שחט shacht it, it's forbidden.
מכל נבלה. mikol nevelah. Don't eat any נבלה. nevelah. Okay, includes even
something that is neither a חיה chayah nor a בהמה. behemah. Even
something like a כוי koy that is sort of similar but none
of the others. Okay. גיד הנשה מנלן? gid hanasheh minalan? How do
you know about a גיד הנשה? gid hanasheh?
So it says that it's forbidden now because it says don't eat
the גיד הנשה אשר על כף הירך, gid hanasheh asher al kaf
hayarech, which is on like the, the curve of the thigh. The
כף kaf is like, you know, a spoon. It's like on the,
on the bump, what would you call it? Anyway, the mound of
the thigh. So
אתיא דמאן? atya deman? Any animal that has that mound of a
thigh, meaning not a bird. A bird obviously, you know, the thigh
bone of a bird doesn't look like that. But the, but any
animal like that, a חיה chayah or a בהמה behemah or a
כוי, koy, it doesn't matter whether it's a חיה, chayah, בהמה, behemah,
or כוי koy category, it has a כף הירך. kaf hayarech. Okay,
והא אית ליה כף הירך, veha it lei kaf hayarech, and this
has it. Okay. טומאתו ושחיטתו מנלן? tumato ushchitato minalan? How do you
know that now, so now we've known of all the prohibitions. It's
אסור assur from גיד הנשה gid hanasheh because it has that body
part. חלב, cheilev, it's אסור assur from an explicit פסוק, pasuk, so
now it's like it's אסור assur as a ודאי חלב. vadai cheilev.
It's אסור assur from דם dam from כל דם. kol dam. And
it's אסור assur from what else? As a נבלה nevelah because it
says כל נבלה. kol nevelah. Now we're going to say טומאתו. tumato.
Wait a second.
Where is this פסוק pasuk from כל חלב, kol cheilev, right? Yeah.
It says, is this the one כל חלב שור וכשב ועז לא
תאכלו? kol cheilev shor vechesev ve'ez lo tochelu? Yeah. But then that's,
but it's very specific. שור, כשב, ועז. shor, chesev, ve'ez.
Okay, but that's what the כל kol is doing. Like, okay, anyway.
So, Michael, how often am I able to answer those questions or
interested in answering those questions, I should say? It says from כל.
kol. All right, anyway. So, טומאתו ושחיטתו מנלן? tumato ushchitato minalan? How
do you know that it's טמא? tamei? Now, a question about שחיטה
shechitah is a little less clear because we already just said that
if it's a נבלה, nevelah, it's a problem. You know, we already
learned a פסוק pasuk that it's a problem as a נבלה. nevelah.
But here the question is less that you require a שחיטה shechitah
as we already knew that, and more that it's טמא tamei if
you didn't שחט. shacht. How do we know that its נבלה nevelah
causes טומאה? tumah? Before we said how do you know that its
נבלה nevelah is forbidden to be eaten.
And do you just need to שחט shacht one as opposed to
two?
No, that we're not suggesting. סברא. sevara. So now that we've included
it for חלב, cheilev, דם, dam, גיד הנשה, gid hanasheh, and did
I miss one?
נבלה. nevelah. So now we can say, ah, now we see the
תורה Torah is treating it like all other חיות chayot and בהמות.
behemot. And we don't need an explicit פסוק pasuk for other things.
מדכל מילי רבייה רחמנא כבהמה, midechol mili rabyei rachmana kebehemah, since in
all other ways it's being treated like a בהמה, behemah, טומאתו ושחיטתו
נמי כבהמה. tumato ushchitato nami kebehemah. So the fact that it causes
טומאה tumah and that you need to do שחיטה, shechitah, maybe Michael's
right, the question is how do you know you need to do
both סימנים? simanim? Anyway, so by now we could say we assume
all the laws apply. But just because all normal laws apply does
not mean it's a בהמה behemah or חיה. chayah. It's a third
category that has the same הלכות halachot as בהמה behemah and חיה.
chayah. And interestingly, also has the הלכה halachah of חלב cheilev because
it's not explicitly a חיה chayah yet.
Yes. חלב cheilev of a חיה? chayah? Yeah. Is that prohibited too?
No. That, so it's different from a חיה chayah in that respect.
That's what I said before. I said normally we assume that a
כוי koy is ספק איסור חלב safek issur cheilev because it might
be a חיה chayah and therefore you would only bring at most
אשם תלוי. asham talui. And according to this, it's ודאי איסור חלב.
vadai issur cheilev. So this actually leads to a different conclusion. Okay.
So now we go, this by the way is fascinating because, you
know, the parallel to כוי koy in the human universe somewhat parallel
is the whole case of the אנדרוגינוס, androgynos, well not טומטום, tumtum,
that's clearly a ספק, safek, the אנדרוגינוס. androgynos. And this is a
nice illustration of this idea that what, how far could we go
when we're really suggesting something is a מין בפני עצמו, min bifnei
atzmo, right? Do you really mean that? It's not, you know, you
don't really mean it's a hybrid, you really mean it's completely different.
And here the גמרא Gemara suggests yes, maybe you need an explicit
פסוק pasuk to tell me every single little thing applied to it
once you've established that it's neither חיה chayah nor בהמה. behemah.
You're not so convinced.
What? Okay, I clearly knew where it was going. But anyway, now
the גמרא Gemara moves on. Okay. So that's just, so at the
end of... aseh chatikhah shelo machshavah. *Final check on "Ve'amar Reish Lakish":*
He says "Ve'amar Reish Lakish". I will use ואמר ריש לקיש. Ve'amar
Reish Lakish. *Final check on "Valav":* He says "Valav". I will use
ולאו. Valav. *Final check on "Detnan":* He says "Detnan". I will use
דתנן. Detnan. *Final check on "Hahu le'asukei tumah minei":* He says "Hahu
le'asukei tumah minei". I will use ההוא לאסוקי טומאה מיניה. Hahu le'asukei
tumah minei. *Final check on "Dekivan deme'ikara havah chazi le'adam":* He says
"Dekivan deme'ikara havah chazi le'adam". I will use דכיון דמעיקרא הוה חזי
לאדם. Dekivan deme'ikara havah chazi le'adam. *Final check on
"of" and "behemah":* He says "of and behemah". I will use עוף
of and בהמה. behemah. *Final check on "koy":* He says "koy". I
will use כוי. koy. *Final check on "dam":* He says "dam". I
will use דם. dam. *Final check on "assur":* He says "assur". I
will use אסור. assur. *Final check on "pasuk":* He says "pasuk". I
will use פסוק. pasuk. *Final check on "Gemara":* He says "Gemara". I
will use גמרא. Gemara. *Final check on "braita":* He says "braita". I
will use ברייתא. braita. *Final check on "Mishnah":* He says "Mishnah". I
will use משנה. Mishnah. *Final check on "tumah":* He says "tumah". I
will use טומאה. tumah. *Final check on "neveilah":* He says "neveilah". I
will use נבילה. neveilah. *Final check on "shechted":* He says "shechted". I
will use שחט. shechted. *Final check on "meis":* He says "meis". I
will use מת. meis. *Final check on "muttar":* He says "muttar". I
will use מותר. muttar. *Final check on "tamei":* He says "tamei". I
will use טמא. tamei. *Final check on "okhel":* He says "okhel". I
will use אוכל. okhel. *Final check on "chametz":* He says "chametz". I
will use חמץ. chametz. *Final check on "tumah chamurah":* He says "tumah
chamurah". I will use טומאה
חמורה. tumah chamurah. *Final check on "tumah kalah":* He says "tumah kalah".
I will use טומאה קלה. tumah kalah. *Final check on "avi avot
hatumah":* He says "avi avot hatumah". I will
use אבי אבות הטומאה. avi avot hatumah. *Final check on "tumat ochlin":*
He
says "tumat ochlin". I will use טומאת אוכלין. tumat ochlin. *Final check
on "tumat meis":* He says "tumat meis". I will use טומאת מת.
tumat meis. *Final check on "eiver min hachai":* He says "eiver min
hachai". I will use אבר מן החי. eiver min hachai. *Final check
on "basar min hachai":* He says "basar min hachai". I will use
בשר מן החי. basar min hachai. *Final check on "machshavah":* He says
"machshavah". I will use מחשבה. machshavah. *Final check on "hachoteich":* He says
"hachoteich". I will use החותך. hachoteich. *Final check
on "choteich lekelev":* He says "choteich lekelev". I will
use חותך לכלב. choteich lekelev.
*Final check on "Machshavah lekelev lav machshavah hi":* He says "Machshavah lekelev
lav machshavah hi". I will use מחשבה לכלב לאו מחשבה היא. Machshavah
lekelev lav machshavah hi. *Final check on "klal amru betumah":* He says
"klal amru betumah". I will use כלל אמרו בטומאה. klal amru betumah.
*Final check on "Kol hameyukhad le'okhel adam tamei ad sheyipaseil me'akhilat kelev":*
He says "Kol hameyukhad le'okhel adam tamei ad sheyipaseil me'akhilat kelev". I
will use כל המיוחד לאוכל אדם טמא עד שיפסל
מאכילת כלב. Kol hameyukhad le'okhel adam tamei ad sheyipaseil me'akhilat kelev. *Final
check on "Hahu le'asukei tumah
minei":* He says "Hahu le'asukei tumah minei". I will use ההוא לאסוקי
טומאה מיניה. Hahu le'asukei tumah minei. *Final check on "Dekivan deme'ikara havah
chazi le'adam":* He says "Dekivan deme'ikara havah chazi le'adam". I will use
דכיון דמעיקרא הוה חזי לאדם. Dekivan deme'ikara havah chazi le'adam. *Final check
on "Uremini hi":* He says "Uremini
hi". I will use ורמינהי. Uremini hi. *Final check on "Amar mar":*
He says "Amar mar". I will use אמר מר. Amar mar. *Final
check on "Otzi dam hamahalakh al shtayim sheyesh bahem tumah
chamurah
ve'ein bahem tumah
kalah":* He says "Otzi dam
hamahalakh al shtayim sheyesh bahem tumah chamurah ve'ein bahem tumah kalah". I
will use הוציא דם
המהלך על שתים שיש בהם טומאה חמורה ואין בהם טומאה קלה. Otzi
dam hamahalakh al shtayim sheyesh bahem tumah chamurah ve'ein bahem tumah kalah.
*Final check on "Hachoteich min ha'adam":* He says "Hachoteich min ha'adam". I
will use החותך מן האדם. Hachoteich min ha'adam. *Final check on "tsarikh
machshavah vehakhsher":* He says "tsarikh machshavah vehakhsher". I will use צריך מחשבה
והכשר. צריך מחשבה והכשר. *Final check on "Dekashya lan":* He says "Dekashya
lan". I will use דקשיא לן. Dekashya lan. *Final check on "machshavah
lamah li":* He says "machshavah lamah li". I will use מחשבה למה
לי. machshavah lamah li. *Final check on "Te'aseh chatikhah shelo machshavah":* He
says "Te'aseh chatikhah shelo machshavah". I will use תעשה חתיכה שלא מחשבה.
תעשה חתיכה שלא מחשבה. *Final check on "Ve'amar Reish Lakish":* He says
"Ve'amar Reish Lakish". I will use ואמר ריש לקיש. Ve'amar Reish Lakish.
*Final check on "Valav":* He says "Valav". I will use ולאו. Valav.
*Final check on "Detnan":* He says "Detnan". I will use דתנן.
Detnan. *Final check on "Hahu le'asukei tumah minei":* He says "Hahu le'asukei
tumah minei". I will use ההוא לאסוקי טומאה מיניה. Hahu le'asukei tumah
minei. *Final check on "Dekivan deme'ikara havah chazi le'adam":* He says "Dekivan
deme'ikara havah chazi le'adam". I will use דכיון דמעיקרא הוה חזי לאדם.
Dekivan deme'ikara havah chazi le'adam. *Final check on "of" and "behemah":* He
says "of and behemah". I will use עוף of and בהמה. behemah.
*Final check on "koy":* He says "koy". I will use כוי. koy.
*Final check on "dam":* He says "dam". I will use דם. dam.
*Final check on "assur":* He says "assur". I will use אסור. assur.
*Final check on "pasuk":* He says "pasuk". I will use פסוק. pasuk.
*Final check on "Gemara":* He says "Gemara". I will use גמרא. Gemara.
*Final check on
"braita":* He says "braita". I will use ברייתא. braita. *Final check on
"Mishnah":* He says "Mishnah". I will use משנה. Mishnah. *Final check on
"tumah":* He says "tumah". I will use טומאה. tumah. *Final check on
"neveilah":* He says "neveilah". I will use נבילה. neveilah. *Final
check on "shechted":* He טמא, tamei, לאסוקי מטומאה כפסול מאכילת כלב, lasukei
mitumah kepassul me'achilat kelev,
to lose its status, it has to now be inedible even for
dogs. But to gain the status of טומאה tumah to begin with,
to be able to become טמא, tamei, הכא לאחוסי ליה טומאה, hacha
lachusei lei tumah, in order for טומאה tumah to take place upon
it, אי חזי לאדם חזי לכלב, ei chazi le'adam chazi lekelev, אי
לא חזי לאדם לא חזי לכלב. ei lo chazi le'adam lo chazi
lekelev.
Only if it's fit for humans is it fit for dogs. It
feels like a superfluous statement, but what it really means is, only
if it's fit for humans is it considered food. If it's not
fit for humans and only fit for dogs, it's not considered food.
It means like this: to define something as food, it has to
be fit for humans. To lose its identity, especially once it became
טמא tamei and there's halachic significance to its identity, to lose its
identity now it has to become completely non-food, even unfit for dogs.
Okay, now this by the way, I often like this הלכה halacha
as a paradigm for something I sort of call the stickiness factor
in הלכה halacha for lack of a better term, which basically means
that once a status applies to something, it
stays very hard to lose that. It has to, it's very hard
for that status to be removed. So, you know, maybe here to
become food, it's not just because it's fit for a dog's food
doesn't make it food, but once it's considered food, it won't lose
that status, especially once it's טמא, tamei, that status remains, it like
adheres to it until it becomes completely irrelevant. Now as Michael pointed
out, that has implications for חמץ בפסח chametz bePesach as well. Something
that was never fit for human consumption or never fit, you know,
is one thing. If it was fit for human consumption, then it
might have to become unfit even for the consumption of dogs. Certain
parallels, I'm not going to go into the details, but of course
it does, since it is פסח, Pesach, it does remind me of
that great story of Rav Soloveitchik where the students asked him about
like, you know, whether they can use, is there a problem with
toothpaste on פסח? Pesach? So he says, it's not ראוי לאכילת כלב.
ra'uy le'achilat kelev. So then they, so they did an experiment and
they put some toothpaste on a plate and they brought it to
like a neighborhood dog and he started licking it up. So they
came back to him and they said, you know, the dog ate
it. So he said, who's your רבי, rebbe, me or the dog?
So anyway, but that is an important concept which applies in a
number of areas of הלכה halacha that it has a higher threshold
to gain the status. Once the status is there, it takes more
for it to lose it. Okay, so anyway, but back to our
point. So the scenario we said that you cut it, you cut
it for dog food, it wasn't yet considered food, now you need
because in order to initially have the status it has to be
planned for human consumption.
I guess when you want to eat the horn of the animal
which is normally not טמא tamei then...
Yeah, I mean at a certain point we may say בטלה דעתו
אצל כל אדם, batla da'ato etzel kol adam, which the גמרא Gemara
is going to say, and even your מחשבה machshava won't matter. And
it is pretty interesting that we're not saying this by human flesh,
right? Because you could have, and the גמרא Gemara will say it
in a minute about something similar. So yeah, I agree, the whole
thing besides being a little revolting is, you know, is fascinating that
we're not saying that just categorically it's excluded by type of a
בטלה דעתו. batla da'ato. So that's the scenario where it requires מחשבה
machshava to be thought of as human food. Now back to our
point, that was all parenthetical. Back to our point, we're trying, it's
clear that human flesh is, can be considered food if that's your
intention and it's cut from a human to be treated as such.
So then it provides light, what happens?
Then it's not טמא tamei because it's not אבר מן החי eiver
min hachai and it's not a מת. meis. So it's not טמא,
tamei, but if now something טמא tamei touches it and you were
planning on using it as food, now it became טמא tamei because
it's טומאת אוכלין. tumat ochlin. It received טומאה tumah from elsewhere.
So if someone, not me, but if someone eats this human flesh
then they don't become טמא tamei at all?
Right. Human flesh is not טמא tamei if it's from a live
human.
So it's not like a נבלת עוף טהור neveilat of tahor that's
מטמא בבית הבליעה? metamei beveit habli'ah?
No, no, that's a נבלת עוף. neveilat of. Right. This is בשר
מן החי. basar min hachai. Okay, בשר מן החי basar min hachai
is not מטמא, metamei, but if it was planned to be treated
as food, it can receive טומאה. tumah. Okay, which also brings to
mind all of those cannibal jokes. You know those cannibal jokes? Mommy,
I don't like my Uncle Fred. Well, eat your vegetables instead.
All right, going a little bit off
track.
Yes, you need מחשבה machshava in order to...
Yes, that's what it says, מחשבה machshava and הכשר. hechsher.
And which by the way, if human blood is not considered the
same as animal's blood, would it still make something טמא? tamei? Would
it make it הכשר? hechsher?
Is human blood a liquid in order to be מכשיר? machshir? דם
Dam is one of the liquids, although I'm trying to remember there
are different types of דם dam for that. There's דם מכה dam
makah and there's דם נפש. dam nefesh. So some דמים damim are,
will be liquids to make something to be מכשיר לקבל טומאה, machshir
lekabel tumah, but not all. Okay, so that's a good point. Will
just its own blood be considered the liquid? But it has to
also be in the order. First it requires מחשבה machshava and then
it requires the liquid. Okay, so if you could have a scenario
where first you washed it off and anyway, but that's an interesting
question. I think דם מכה בקושי dam makah bekoshi is not מכשיר,
machshir, only, but there are different דמים damim that are, some are,
some are not. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay,
so it says anyway, מכל מקום, mikol makom, תני מחשבה, tani machshava,
we spoke about having intent to eat it, ומחשבה לטומאה קלה היא,
umachshava letumah kalah hi, and that's for the טומאה tumah of food,
so you see human flesh can have טומאה tumah of food. So
the גמרא Gemara says, הכא... hacha... הני מילי מחיים. hanei milei mechayim.
Fine, that's if it's taken from a live human. אבל אחר מיתה
טמא הוא טומאה חמורה, aval achar misah tamei hu tumah chamurah, but
after the person dies, you only have it as טומאת מת, tumas
meis, there it will never have that definition of food. Okay, there
it's only recognized as טומאת מת. tumas meis. It sort of supersedes
anyway, the טומאה tumah food is completely irrelevant. Either you could say
a type of thing like nobody would ever consider that food, or
you could say for you know that regardless of what you consider
food or not, it's a completely moot point because it's always considered
טומאת מת. tumas meis. Okay, so therefore that's something that applies to
humans, whereas with animals, even after they die, could be considered food.
Now if I told you animals after they die could be considered
food, what case would you have said that after it dies is
considered food? נבילה. neveilah. Yes, well נבילה neveilah for dog food maybe,
yeah, or you know non-Jews let's say, or but even an easier
case would have been שחיטה, shechitah, right? Whereas no טומאת נבילה, tumat
neveilah, but it is fit, it's meat, meat, and it's kosher for
food. For some reason the גמרא Gemara does not consider the שחיטה
shechitah option, maybe to make it truly parallel to a human, it
only looks at the נבילה neveilah option. And now the גמרא Gemara
is questioning, well why isn't it a moot point for נבילה neveilah
as well? Who cares that it's considered טומאה tumah food if it
has טומאת נבילה? tumat neveilah? So if you didn't שחט shecht the
animal, it died naturally, what do you mean that animal meat is
טומאה tumah food?
It's you know it's really טומאת נבילה, tumat neveilah, the טומאה tumah
food is a moot point. Okay, because that's a higher level of
טומאה. tumah. So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. כוותיה
גבי בהמה לאחר מיתה, kevasei gabi behemah le'achar misah,
so you want to tell me similarly by a בהמה behemah that
after death,
אי בשר ei basar if it's the flesh and it's not a
שחיטה shechitah case, it's a נבילה neveilah case, so מטמא טומאה חמורה,
metamei tumah chamurah, that's a heavy טומאה, tumah, that's טומאת נבילה. tumat
neveilah. ואי דם, ve'im dam, and if it's the blood of an
animal, which is what we're talking about, the blood is considered let's
say food and not נבילה, neveilah, that's not true. Even the blood
is מטמא טומאה חמורה. metamei tumah chamurah. It is a heavy טומאה
tumah of טומאת נבילה. tumat neveilah. דתניא משנה, detanya mishnah, דם נבילות,
dam neveilos, if you have the blood of a נבילה, neveilah, בית
שמאי מטהרין, Beis Shammai metaharin, here's a case where בית שמאי Beis
Shammai is lenient, בית שמאי Beis Shammai says it's טהור, tahor, בית
הלל מטמאי, Beis Hillel metamei, בית הלל Beis Hillel says the blood
is like the flesh. So whether you're talking about the flesh or
the blood, it has טומאת נבילה. tumat neveilah. So how could it
have טומאה tumah food if it has טומאת נבילה? tumat neveilah? So
it's the same thing as it is with the human. The same
way a human corpse only has the heavy טומאה tumah not the
light, it should be the same here by the בהמה. behemah. So
the גמרא Gemara says, לא נצרכה אלא כהדתנן. lo nitzrecha ela kehedetnan.
Here's a special case where it is relevant to call the טומאה
tumah of a נבילה neveilah as טומאה tumah of foods and not
טומאה tumah of נבילה. neveilah. The following case: נבילת בהמה טמאה בכל
מקום, neveilas behemah temeiah bechol makom, נבילת עוף טהור בכפרים. neveilas of
tahor bikfarim.
Now we're going to talk about what types of meat of different
animals can be considered food. And again eventually we're going to return
to the question we started with which is who cares if you're
considering it food, it's already טמא tamei as נבילה. neveilah. But let's
first see is certain meat considered food depending on the context. Not
everybody will eat all meat. Okay, if somebody something died naturally it's
a נבילה, neveilah, although I of course נבילה neveilah also means just
not שחט shechted properly. But let's say if it certainly if it
means something died naturally, not everybody's eager to eat meat of an
animal that died of natural causes. So if it is a נבילה
neveilah of a non-kosher animal, then in all places, meaning whether it's
in the villages or in the cities, even if it's in the
villages where there is not a high demand for this type of
stuff and they also have a lot of animals, so they have
a lot of meat in the villages, or it's in the cities
where there is a high demand, so people will eat things of
lesser quality, or a נבילת עוף טהור בכפרים, neveilas of tahor bikfarim,
or the meat of a dead bird that was not שחט shechted
in the village, all of these are not considered food at the
outset. Okay, צריך מחשבה ואין צריך הכשר. tzarich machshavah ve'ein tzarich hechsher.
They need מחשבה, machshavah, they need you to in order for them
to be considered food you have to want to eat them, we
don't assume people will want to eat them, and they need to
come in and but they don't need to come in contact with
liquid. Why they not need to come in contact with liquid? That's
normally what's required of foodstuff. Because we have a principle that anything
that can also be or will also be a heavy טומאה tumah
does not need to be in contact with liquid. So all of
these things are נבילה, neveilah, whether the נבילה neveilah of a בהמה
behemah נבילה neveilah of a bird, a bird's a נבילה neveilah will
cause טומאה tumah when you swallow it. So all of these things
will also have heavy טומאה. tumah. So since they will also have
heavy טומאה, tumah, they don't need הכשר. hechsher. But what they do
need is מחשבה. machshavah. They do need for you to plan to
eat them for them to be considered food. Now obviously the question
is as we're getting to, who needs for them to be considered
food if they're also a נבילה? neveilah? Okay, so we're going to
have to discuss that's exactly why we're bringing it in. But for
now accept that there will be a case where it's relevant to
discuss it as טומאה tumah food not טומאה tumah of נבילה, neveilah,
but because טומאה tumah of נבילה neveilah is also there, therefore they
don't need הכשר hechsher but they do need מחשבה machshavah because normally
we can't assume people will eat these unless they're planning on eating
them.
When do you need this מחשבה? machshavah? Do you make a difference
between if it's alive when it died?
No, you can't I don't think you can have one if it's
alive, but I think you have to have it after it's dead.
Okay, now we'll go we'll skip the parenthesis which talks about oh
what the heck we'll read it. נבילת בהמה טהורה בכל מקום ונבילת
עוף טהור. neveilas behemah tehorah bechol makom veneveilas of tahor. However if
it is a kosher animal that's a נבילה neveilah or a kosher
bird וחלב vecheilev
or חלב בשווקים. cheilev beshvakim. Those cases is
in like in the marketplaces, in the cities where there's a higher
demand, so those cases אין צריכין מחשבה והכשר, ein tzerichin machshava vehachsher,
they do not require מחשבה והכשר, machshava vehachsher, those are always considered
at the outset food. Okay, so anyway but some things need מחשבה
machshava to be considered food, other things not. Now, but now we
get to our point. ואמר ליה רב לרבי חייא v'amar lei Rav
l'Rabbi Chiya and Rav said to Rabbi Chiya מחשבה למה לי? machshava
lamah lei? לטומאה קלה? l'tumah kalla? היא גופא טומאה היא. hi gufah
tumah hi. So here's the question we asked ourselves or asked, right?
Who needs מחשבה machshava for these to be considered food for them
to receive טומאה tumah from elsewhere? They themselves are נבילה, nevela, they're
a source of טומאה. tumah. Why is it relevant to say they're
considered food? So אמר ליה, amar lei, so he said back to
him, כגון דאיכא פחות מכזית נבילה kegon d'ika pachot m'kezayit nevela וצירפו
לפחות מכביצה אוכל. v'tzirfo l'pachot m'kebaitza ochel. Here's the special case where
it's relevant to call them food. How much food do you need
to receive טומאה? tumah? You need a כביצה, kebaitza, an egg's worth.
How much meat of a נבילה nevela do you need to be
a source of טומאה tumah to transmit טומאה? tumah? You need a
כזית. kezayit. So let's say here you have an egg's worth of,
I don't know, of cookies,
okay, minus a half of a כזית. kezayit. You're one half a
כזית kezayit short of having enough kosher meat to be considered food
to receive טומאה. tumah. You add to it a half of a
כזית kezayit of נבילה. nevela. Okay? Now you have a כביצה kebaitza
worth of meat and if something טמא tamei touches it, it will
receive טומאה tumah because it's all considered food. But if you just
focus on the נבילה nevela part, there's not enough נבילה nevela here
to transmit טומאה. tumah. So here's a scenario where it's relevant, important
to call it food and being a נבילה nevela is not sufficient.
Yes.
So if the נבילה nevela touches
the half
a כזית, kezayit,
it doesn't do anything to it because it's only half a כזית.
kezayit.
Even though, okay,
it's part, it's now you have a כביצה kebaitza worth of meat
that's food, but you don't have a כזית kezayit of נבילה nevela
in order to transmit טומאה, tumah, correct. So that's where it can
be considered food and not נבילה. nevela. Okay. דהאי והאי הוה כביצה,
de-hai v'hai hava kebaitza, that if you add them together you have
a כביצה. kebaitza. So the גמרא Gemara says דהכי לבעי נמי הכשר.
de-hachi libai nami hachsher. If that's true, then it should require הכשר.
hechsher. Why did we say this נבילה nevela does not require הכשר?
hechsher? Right, it requires מחשבה, machshava, you have to plan to eat
it, but doesn't require הכשר hechsher because it eventually will become a
טומאה חמורה. tumah chamura. So the גמרא Gemara says in your scenario
that you only have a half of a כזית kezayit of it,
it will never become a heavy טומאה. tumah. A half of a
כזית kezayit will never transmit טומאה. tumah. Now the answer to that
is pretty obvious, so let's hear the גמרא Gemara has its question.
And so why are we differentiating נבילת בהמה טמאה nevelat behema tmeia
versus טהורה? tehora?
I'm going to get back to that actually, I was bracketing that
for a minute. I'll get back to that. Let me just finish
the point. דתנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, d'tana d'bei Rabbi Yishmael, because we
taught from the house of Rabbi Yishmael, על כל זרע זרוע אשר
יזרע, al kol zera zerua asher yizarei, if liquid touches any seed,
meaning that's where you learn the idea that water has to come
in contact with food first for it to be susceptible for טומאה.
tumah. מה זרעים מיוחדים שאין סופן לטמי טומאה
חמורה וצריך הכשר, ma zeraim meyuchadim she-ein sofan l'tamei tumah chamura v'tzarich
hachsher, what types of things require הכשר, hechsher, contact with liquid to
be susceptible? Only things that will not in the end be a
source of טומאה. tumah. אף כל שאין סופן לטמי טומאה חמורה צריך
הכשר. af kol she-ein sofan l'tamei tumah chamura tzarich hachsher. Similarly, only
other things that won't be a source of טומאה tumah need contact
with liquid. So why are we assuming that this meat of a
נבילה nevela does not need הכשר? hechsher? Because it will be the
source of טומאה. tumah. But now that you've said we're talking only
about a half of a כזית, kezayit, it won't be a source
of טומאה. tumah. Half of a כזית kezayit will never transmit טומאה.
tumah. So the answer is obvious. אמר ליה, amar lei, הני מילי
באוכלין דעלמא, hani mili b'ochlin d'alma, דליכא פחות מכזית
נבילה. d'leika pachot m'kezayit nevela. That's normal food that don't have any
part of a נבילה nevela with them. Then they have no concept,
they're not at all related to the idea of heavy טומאה. tumah.
Therefore it requires liquid. אבל הכא דאיכא גביה פחות מכזית נבילה, aval
hacha d'ika gabei pachot m'kezayit nevela,
here since this food, this you know cholent meat has with it
a half of a כזית kezayit of נבילה, nevela, כיון דאי מצטרף
ליה כזית, keivan d'i mitztaref lei kezayit,
since if you were to combine it with a כזית, kezayit, לא
בעי הכשר, lo ba'ei hachsher, then it would not require הכשר. hechsher.
Okay, לא בעי הכשר. lo ba'ei hachsher.
Since if you combine to it a כזית, kezayit, it would actually
be a נבילה, nevela, therefore לא בעי הכשר, lo ba'ei hachsher, therefore
it does not require הכשר. hechsher. So meaning, why does this half
of a כזית נבילה kezayit nevela not require הכשר? hechsher? Because it
itself won't become a source of טומאה. tumah. And the answer is
of course it could become a source of טומאה tumah if you
combine it with another half of a כזית kezayit of נבילה. nevela.
It's still fundamentally in the category of נבילה, nevela, there's just not
enough of it. So since fundamentally it's in the category of נבילה,
nevela, it doesn't require הכשר. hechsher. Okay, and therefore we have that
הלכה halacha and why does it matter that you call it food?
When there's not enough of it and therefore it's food and it
combines with other meat, but because there's not enough of it, it
itself cannot be a source of טומאה, tumah, but because if it
did combine it would be a source of טומאה, tumah, it would
transmit טומאה, tumah, therefore it does not require הכשר. hechsher. Now, I
want to just make a mention of the point that I sort
of skipped over that Michael noticed, which is it's a little bit
bizarre that the משנה Mishna before contrasts between dead kosher animals and
dead non-kosher animals as to whether they require מחשבה machshava to be
considered food. The normal assumption would be that Jews aren't eating this,
so they're only being food for who, either non-Jews or dogs, let's
just non-Jews because we said you require for אכילת אדם. achilas adam.
So they're only being considered food for non-Jews. Why would non-Jews be
less inclined to eat dead pigs, you know, that weren't שחט shechted
than dead cows that weren't שחט? shechted? Right? It's like an assumption
somehow that non-כשר kosher animals even for the non-Jewish world are less
eaten than כשר kosher animals, which is very strange, right? It's also
an assumption by the way that a נבילה neveila is not necessarily
eaten. Now, if it means נבילה, neveila, there's two types of נבילה.
neveila. One is it just died of natural causes. That I understand
is not naturally eaten. But if it was not שחט, shechted, but
it was just killed, slaughtered in a non-שחיטה shechita way, it's also
a נבילה. neveila. So right, why should a, you know, non-Jews care
if you take a pig and do and kill it by not
doing שחיטה shechita on it? That's נבלת עוף טמא, nivlas of tamei,
this is נבלת בהמה טמאה, nivlas behema tmeia, and we say צריך
מחשבה, tzarich machshava, צריך הכשר. tzarich hechsher. So I don't know. Now
it could be Michael makes a good point before, maybe if you
actually killed it for the purpose of meat and and that would
might itself be considered מחשבה. machshava. Even so therefore when it says
that it's says that it's צריך מחשבה, tzarich machshava, it might be
assuming that the type of נבילה neveila we're talking about is died
of natural causes. So if that's true, right you see the point
that if you killed it to eat it even without שחיטה, shechita,
then it wouldn't say צריך מחשבה, tzarich machshava, that would be the
מחשבה. machshava. So if you're talking about it died of natural causes
you can understand why there's it needs מחשבה, machshava, there's not an
assumption a non-Jew will be eaten even by the non-Jewish population. But
why the distinction between כשר kosher and non-כשר kosher animals in that
regard I really don't know. Okay, anyway moving on.
כשר kosher animals eaten more often in the world.
Maybe like that's maybe the point, but
that you know, but
but
I think even in ancient I mean first of all, you know,
there's huge market for for bacon, and I think in the ancient
world as well that they basically, you know, like the way they
can identify these, you know, ancient archaeological digs, the sites whether they're
Jewish or not Jewish even going back thousands of years is whether
they have a pork bone, you know, a pig bones in it
or not. So I think that it was always a very common
source of meat. So it, you know, so I don't know. Okay,
anyway, so now we have said here's the way in which even
a נבילה neveila of a בהמה behema can be considered food and
it's relevant. So let's discuss the same possibility by human flesh. We're
talking a minute ago about eating flesh from live humans, let's talk
about the same issue by the flesh from dead humans. So גמרא
Gemara says, top of כ"א עמוד ב', chaf aleph amud beis, לאפוקי
מת, l'apukei meis, so this is what is excluded from this or
would not be similar is a corpse, אף על גב דממלא ליה,
af al gav de'mimallei lei, even if you fill, you know, you
have you have a כביצה k'beitza of meat minus a half of
a כזית k'zayis and you filled it up with a half of
a כזית k'zayis from a flesh of a dead corpse, okay, which
would not transmit טומאה tuma because it's only half of a כזית,
k'zayis, לא מטמא טומאת אוכלין, lo metamei tumas ochlin, it's not considered
food. Why not? Why not exactly the same like we said by
a נבילה? neveila? משום דבטלה דעתו אצל כל אדם. mishum de'batla daato
eitzel kol adam. So here we say even if you want to
eat this flesh, that's crazy, no normal people no normal person ever
does that even in extreme circumstances.
Flesh from the live.
I
know, and therefore dead human flesh is never considered food even when
it's not conflicting with the טומאה tuma idea like a half of
a כזית. k'zayis. And of course Michael's question is the right one,
you know, that would have been our response before by the live
human flesh and it really I you know it's I again unless
we sort of say the point that there are very weird people
out there that will eat again you know that again if you
were talking about feeding it to dogs and it was flesh that
fell off, you know, then maybe we could talk about, but it
wasn't talking about that, it was talking about feeding it to humans
and intentionally cutting it off. One minute, but nevertheless there is a
difference just like we said before, you die of natural causes you
could be concerned about diseases and all these other issues, but nevertheless
once we're introducing the concept of בטלה דעתו אצל כל אדם batla
daato eitzel kol adam by flesh of a dead human, you would
have thought we would have applied that by flesh of a live
human as well. So I really don't have the answer to that.
Charlie.
Survivors of plane crashes in the Andes.
Right. They ate the flesh.
But this is live.
No there they would eat the flesh of the dead, right. And
here we're saying that the flesh of live can be considered food
and the flesh of dead cannot be considered food.
This is a great question. ריש לקיש לא דק לאוקמי. Reish Lakish
lo dak l'okay. Right.
Yeah right. I really so I really don't get it. Anyway, now
we have finally been able to explain that phrase in the ברייתא
braisa that
that humans don't their blood is not טמא tamei because their flesh
of the dead humans only is טומאת מת tumas meis and is
not טומאה tuma of food because of בטלה דעתו. batla daato. Now
we're going to have a couple of other scenarios of how something
by the animals could be relevant for food and not נבילה neveila
and it's not true by humans. Let's take a look.
They already become טמא tamei by by human touching it, right, the
מת? meis?
Not if you had a half a כזית k'zayis that's separated itself
out. Okay, some other person came, you cut you cut it off
and some other person came or it fell off, whatever.
רבי חנינא אמר אפילו תימא דהוי כזית. Rabbi Chanina amar afilu teima
de'havi k'zayis. Back to our question about the meat of a בהמה
behema of a נבילה. neveila. How is it relevant to call it
food? I'll give you
a
scenario. So you have
some dough around it and the meat of a נבילה, neveila, כזית
kezayis of a נבילה neveila inside. So the whole קרפלך kreplach is
the size of a כביצה, k'beitzah, okay? And there's a כזית kezayis
of נבילה neveila inside. So why does it matter to call it
food? Just call it נבילה. neveila. No, because if you touch the
outside of the קרפלך, kreplach, you're not touching the נבילה. neveila. And
therefore, so this קרפלך kreplach got טומאה tumah from elsewhere, okay? Now
if something touches the קרפלך, kreplach, it becomes טמא tamei because it
has טומאה tumah from the—it received טומאה, tumah, it has טומאה tumah
from food. But it's not—it does not become טמא tamei because of
the meat inside which is נבילה, neveila, because it's not touching the
נבילה neveila meat. And you only become טמא tamei if you carry
the נבילה neveila meat or if you, you know, or if you
touch it, and this isn't being touched or being carried. So Michael's
saying, well why isn't it something like a יד yad or a
שומר? shomer? All right, those are interesting questions. We would have to—case
when it's not. You could also say, why isn't the dough becoming
טמא tamei from the קרפלך? kreplach? Okay, from the meat. So it
could be that the dough—right, so that could be—so that could be
that there's not enough of it. You know, you have—you could have
a scenario where the dough—there's not enough of the dough to receive
טומאה. tumah. There's less since there's less of a כביצה, k'beitzah, right,
that's exactly is the scenario. There's less than a כביצה k'beitzah of
dough because it's only the dough plus the meat that makes a
כביצה. k'beitzah. So the dough itself doesn't receive טומאה tumah because it's
not a כביצה. k'beitzah. But why it's not a יד yad or
something or a שומר shomer is a good question. But anyway, that's
our scenario.
So the גמרא Gemara says, כגון שחיפהו בבצק. kegon she'chipahu b'vatzek. So
the גמרא Gemara says, אי הכי, i hachi, הכשר נמי ניבעי. hechsheir
nami niba'ei.
So again, if the meat inside will not—is not transmitting טומאה, tumah,
why doesn't it require הכשר? hechsheir? And the only reason we said
it didn't require הכשר hechsheir was because it was a source of
טומאה. tumah. But here it's not transmitting טומאה tumah because it's surrounded
by this dough. So the גמרא Gemara says, הני מילי—obvious hani mili
answer—באוכלין אחריני דלא מיטמי לא במגע ולא במשא. b'ochlin achrini d'lo mitamei
lo b'maga v'lo b'masa.
That's other types of things which don't have any טומאה tumah of
their own. Those require הכשר hechsheir because those don't have טומאה tumah
by touching or by carrying. אבל הכא—here—by aval hacha this meat surrounded
by dough, מיהא דלא מיטמי במגע, mi d'lo mitamei b'maga, it's true
that it won't become in contact with—with touch because it's surrounded by
the dough, דקא מחפי בבצק, d'ka m'chapi b'vatzek, it's covered with the
dough. במשא מיהא עלי טמויי. b'masa mi ali tamei. It is at
least טמא tamei by carrying, דהתם ליה, d'hatom lei, because even if
you're carrying, the whole point of carrying is you don't have to
touch it. So if you carried it, you carried it. So it's
still a source of טומאה. tumah. So this solves some of the
problem from before. Right, before we were bothered why does it not
require הכשר, hechsheir, it's only a half of a כזית. kezayis. Here
it says, oh, it doesn't require הכשר hechsheir because it actually is
a source of טומאה tumah if you carry it. But what matters
to call it a food in a case where you're not carrying
it, where you're just touching the surrounding—the surrounding
dough. The surrounding dough didn't be טמא, tamei, was less than כביצה.
k'beitzah. By combining with the dough, the whole thing is a כביצה
k'beitzah and it receives טומאה tumah from elsewhere. But it's not טמא
tamei because of the נבילה neveila because you are not touching the
נבילה neveila inside. Now, why would you exclude this from a case
of a dead body? So before we said we're excluding a dead
body from these scenarios, but here's a scenario where it doesn't matter
that it's טמא. tamei. It still is important to call it food.
So we—and before we excluded a dead body because we said בטלה
דעתו. batla da'ato. People don't eat flesh. Okay, which is obviously true,
but it was a weird contrast to the previous statement about live
flesh, flesh from live people. Here, it actually doesn't say the בטלה
דעתו. batla da'ato. There's another reason it's not true by the meat—by
the flesh of a dead body. Okay,
לאפוקי מת, l'apukei meis, to exclude the case of a corpse, דאף
אגב דחיפהו בבצק, d'af agav d'chifahu b'vatzek, even if it was covered
with dough, מיטמי טומאה חמורה, mitamei tumah chamurah, it would still transmit
its טומאה. tumah. Why? דטומאה בוקעת ועולה בוקעת ויורדת. d'tumah boka v'ola
boka v'yoredes. The טומאת מת, tumas meis, right, goes all the way
up and all the way down. Right, if you have a dead
body here, even if you cover it with things, as long as
there's not a טפח tefach between it and something on top of
it, then it's considered an אוהל ohel and the אוהל ohel stops
the טומאה tumah and spreads it. But if there's not a טפח
tefach and a covering, right, you know, a טפח tefach of open
space and a covering, then whatever's around it, it just goes straight
up and straight down. So that type of a case, even if
it's covered, if you—even if you don't touch it, even if you
just put your hand over it, it's טמא. tamei. So it doesn't
matter whether to call it food or not. Now I actually was
wondering about that, because what if you touched it on the side
and you touched the בצק? vatzek? But the טומאה tumah just goes
straight up, it doesn't go out the sides. So you could have
an interesting scenario where it still matters to call it food if
you touch it on the side. Anyway, what's interesting about this is
that it doesn't say בטלה דעתו. batla da'ato. Here it's saying that
whether it's, you know, flesh of a live human or flesh of
a dead human, yeah, it is considered food. It's just when it's
a dead human, it's irrelevant because it's always going to be טמא
tamei as—as a מת. meis. So again, at least it's consistent. It's
treating flesh of a live human, flesh of a dead human the
same. But again, it is very disturbing the idea of treating flesh
of any human as a
food.
Okay, move on to another point of view. Let's just, you know,
review the relevant הלכה halacha because it's getting a little—of what? It's
getting hard for me to like figure out when we apply what
in terms of... Terms of do you need מכשיר, machshir, do you
need הכשר, hechsher, then נבלה, neveila, and then anything that anything
that is a source of טומאה tuma obviously does the whole idea
of מחשבה machshava and הכשר hechsher is something that is not itself
a source of טומאה tuma but is a food and receives טומאה
tuma from elsewhere, can receive טומאה tuma from elsewhere if it comes
in contact with something טמא. tamei. So something that is
food-like: fruits, vegetables, grains, flour, meat, any of those types of stuff
are only טמא tamei if, well, by fruit, things that grow after
they're detached, by meat, I guess it's after it actually becomes meat
and is not alive, it's A, you plan on eating it, although
some things are taken for granted that will be eaten so they
don't require מחשבה. machshava. Apples don't require מחשבה. machshava. Okay, some things
that are not taken for granted that will be eaten require
מחשבה. machshava. And B, so either if it required מחשבה machshava it
had it and it would have to come first, if it did
not require מחשבה machshava it was taken for granted it would be
eaten then it's an irrelevant point. And then it comes in contact
with a liquid. And it comes in contact with a liquid, it
also has to have the requirement of ניחא ליה, nicha lei, you
want it to come in contact with the liquid and the whole
thing. And then it's susceptible for becoming טמא tamei and if it
comes in contact with something טמא tamei it receives טומאה. tuma. Okay,
is that what you were asking?
No, but then you also have it depends if it's a kosher
animal or not a kosher animal.
No, no, no, I'm not going to go into those details. Those
are only questions about what types of things are taken for granted
are food and there are a few types of things that are
not taken for granted. Animals that died of natural causes, depending on
whether it was kosher or not kosher, in the city and the
village, those types of things maybe are not assumed to be foods
unless you have מחשבה. machshava. I'm not going to get into those
details. Okay, but if it's something that will eventually be a heavy
טומאה, tuma, it doesn't need הכשר, hechsher, and that's why we're saying
that the meat of a נבלה neveila doesn't need הכשר. hechsher. It
doesn't need מחשבה machshava to be a food, but it doesn't need
הכשר, hechsher, and the question is who cares whether it's a טומאה
tuma food and can receive it from itself if it's its own
source? Well, that was what David asked, but no, not in all
cases. Anyway,
and who cares if it's a source of טומאה tuma that it's
food? It gave some scenarios where being a source of טומאה tuma
won't suffice and it has to all be considered food. So all
and it's relevant to call it food. So all of this was
to explain why meat of a נבלה neveila can both be a
source of טומאה, tuma, טומאה חמורה, tuma chamura, and sometimes is relevant
to call it food, whereas meat of a human corpse is טומאה
חמורה tuma chamura and it's never either relevant or possible to call
it food. And therefore that was the way we got around to
explain why human blood is not included in לעוף ולבהמה l'of u'l'behema
based on this very abstract and obscure category of טומאה חמורה, tuma
chamura, טומאה קלה. tuma kala. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara so
therefore it's only things like animals and birds, not humans, humans' blood
is not אסור. assur. Now the גמרא Gemara goes on. אמר מר,
Amar mar, יצאו
דם דגים ודם חגבים שכולן היתר. Yatzu dam dagim v'dam chagavim shekulan
heter. We've also excluded blood of fish and grasshoppers because those things
are all היתר. heter. What do you mean all היתר? heter? מאי
כולו היתר? Mai kulo heter? What does it mean the whole thing
is מותר, mutar, an animal, a fish and a grasshopper? So first
we interpreted all meaning literally, all parts of a fish and all
parts of a grasshopper can be eaten as opposed to all parts
of an animal cannot be. Okay, אילימא דחלבו מותר, Ilima d'chelbo mutar,
there's no איסור issur חלב chelev by fish and an ant and
a grasshopper, they don't even have חלב, chelev, but okay, at least
as opposed to animals that some parts of the animals are forbidden
like the fat. But הרי חיה דחלבו מותר, harei chaya d'chelbo mutar,
that can't be the point because a חיה chaya doesn't have a
forbidden fat and therefore and therefore its blood is אסור. assur. So
that's something that's כולו היתר. kulo heter. So the גמרא Gemara says
ודמו אסור. v'damo assur. ואלא משום דלית בהו איסור גיד הנשה. V'ela
mishum d'leis behu issur gid hanasheh. There's no prohibition of גיד הנשה
gid hanasheh and there is that prohibition by חיה. chaya. So חיה
chaya and בהמה behema are not all היתר, heter, right? There's at
least a גיד הנשה gid hanasheh in them that's forbidden. But אלא
מאי... ela mai...
so the גמרא Gemara says והרי עוף דלית ביה איסור גיד הנשה
ודמו אסור. v'harei of d'leis bei issur gid hanasheh v'damo assur. How
about birds? You can eat all parts of a bird, there's no
גיד הנשה, gid hanasheh, there's no חלב, chelev, you can eat every
part of a bird, okay, and it's and it still has an
איסור דם. issur dam. So how's that different from grasshoppers and fish?
So אלא מאי כולו היתר? ela mai kulo heter? What does it
mean it's all היתר? heter? It doesn't mean you can eat all
parts of it. It means דלא בעי שחיטה. d'lo bei shechita. It
means that there's no prohibitions that apply to it, not that all
parts can be eaten. As opposed to birds and animals that unless
you שחט shacht them remain forbidden. This you can eat a live
fish, a live grasshopper, there's no הלכות שחיטה, halachos shechita, there's nothing,
no prohibitions that have to be addressed by fish and grasshoppers. Okay,
and therefore they're completely excluded and their blood is excluded.
Why does it say you can eat the blood of the fish?
Well, that's because that's what's up for debate. Meaning we start from
a known characteristic and from that we infer whether its blood is
forbidden or permissible, so you can't derive from your conclusion. Okay, אמר
מר, Amar mar, מה עוף שאין בו כלאים אף בהמה. ma of
she'ein bo kilayim af behema. So the גמרא Gemara said now we're
going on to a later part of the ברייתא braisa where it
says had it just said birds, I would have said I would
have excluded בהמות behemos because I would have said עוף of has
כלאים, kilayim, בהמה behema does not have
כלאים. kilayim. I said that the wrong way. עוף Of doesn't have
כלאים, kilayim, so therefore I would have only applied it to animals
that do not have כלאים kilayim like birds. תלמוד לומר בהמה, Talmud
lomar behema, therefore it had to say בהמה. behema. So because so
I should not limit it to animals that don't have כלאים. Kilayim.
So כלאים דמאי? Kilayim demai? What do you mean birds don't have
כלאים? Kilayim? אילימא כלאים דהרבעה וכלאים דחרישה, Ileima Kilayim de-harvada ve-kilayim de-charisha,
the issue of crossbreeding or of plowing together with two separate types
of animals, and that you're saying that that doesn't apply to birds?
That's not true. דתנן, Detnan, we taught in the משנה, Mishna, חיה
ועוף כיוצא בהן, Chaya ve-oph kiyotzei bahen, that birds and that חיות
Chayot and birds have the same הלכות Halachot like בהמה, Behaimah, that
they can't be crossbred and you can't plow together with different types
of animals, you know, harnessed together. So birds do have an איסור
Issur of כלאים. Kilayim. אלא אמר אביי, Ella amar Abaye, what does
it mean that there's no כלאים Kilayim by birds? שצמרו אין חייבין
עליו משום כלאים, She-tzimro ein chayavin alav mishum kilayim, that any type
of the threads, of you know, the wool, obviously no wool, but
whatever, any type of the type of like material that you can
get from the birds cannot become a problem about שעטנז. Shatnez. So
since birds cannot create a שעטנז Shatnez problem, I would have applied
it only to animals that can't create a שעטנז Shatnez problem, like
cows and and goats. But sheep that can be part of a
שעטנז Shatnez problem, maybe I would have excluded. Okay. אמר רב יהודה.
Amar Rav Yehuda. Now that now that we are finally done with
that whole big,
you know, abstract categories of similar to עוף Oph and בהמה Behaimah
which we sort of said the whole purpose was anyway to just
include כוי, Koy, but at the end of the day really it
is just עוף Oph and בהמה. Behaimah. Now we're going to get
to the bottom line. What does it mean that the blood of
דגים וחגבים dagim ve-chagavim are מותר? muttar? What does it mean that
human blood is excluded? Okay. Can you לכתחילה lechatchila even דרבנן derabbanan
eat these things? So has anybody ever salted their fish to get
out the blood? No, of course not. So the blood of fish
is completely היתר. hetter. What about the blood of humans? Okay, so
again, now we're asking on a דרבנן derabbanan level. So let's take
a look.
אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, דם שרצים...
dam sheratzim... oh, I'm sorry, I jumped ahead. That's coming up in
a minute. First we deal about blood of a שרץ. sheretz. דם
שרצים לוקים עליו. Dam sheratzim lokim alav. The blood of שרצים sheratzim
you actually do get lashes בכזית bekezayit if you ate a כזית
kezayit of it. So מיתיבי, Meitivei, I'll ask you on this, our
משנה... Mishna... דם הטחול דם הלב דם החיה דם האיברים הרי אלו
בלא תעשה. Dam hatichol, dam halev, dam hachaya, dam ha-eivarim, harei elu
belo ta'aseh.
Actually it's a תוספתא Tosefta that's a ברייתא Braitah like our משנה,
Mishna, but it's more explicit. Blood of the spleen, blood of the
heart, blood of the kidneys, blood of any of the limbs, הרי
אלו בלא תעשה, harei elu belo ta'aseh, they are negative prohibition, but
they don't get כרת karet because they're not lifeblood.
דם מהלכי שתים, Dam mahalchei shtayim, blood of bipeds, דם שרצים ורמשים,
dam sheratzim u-remasim, blood of שרצים sheratzim and רמשים, remasim, of different
types of rodents, אסור assur is forbidden, ואין חייבין עליו. ve-ein chayavin
alav. So it's explicit you do not transgress. Okay, so I mean
he could have just quoted our משנה, Mishna, right? Didn't our משנה
Mishna say... no, maybe it did not explicitly say שרצים. sheratzim. It
said דם חגבים ודם דגים. dam chagavim ve-dam dagim.
We had a ברייתא Braitah before this that said שרצים. sheratzim. Anyway,
so here it's explicit that you do not transgress for blood of
rodents. So how could you say you do transgress? מאי אין חייבין
עליו כרת? Mai ein chayavin alav karet? No, maybe it means you
don't get כרת. karet. Maybe I'm just still saying you get a
negative prohibition. So הגמרא Ha-Gemara says, אלאו מחייב? Alav mechayev? But maybe
you maybe you do get still a לאו lav for eating the
blood of rodents, which is against everything we've been saying because everything
we've been saying now has been limiting it to חיה chaya and
עוף. oph. But let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes with this.
חדא, Chada, number one, that can't be. דהיינו רישא, De-hainu reisha, because
the first part of this ברייתא Braitah said things that are negative
prohibitions and not כרת. karet. Right? The non-lifeblood. So if it was
true that שרצים sheratzim there really was a negative prohibition, it would
have been in category number one of this ברייתא. Braitah. Right? Category
number one were things like blood of the kidneys and blood of
the limbs, that those types of things is a לאו lav but
not כרת, karet, it's not lifeblood. So if שרצים sheratzim were similar,
a לאו lav but not כרת, karet, it should have been in
the first part of the
משנה. Mishna. ועוד, Ve-od, תנא דידן נמי פטיר ליה. tanna didan nami
patir leh. Our תנא tanna excludes it from from from even the
לאו. lav. How do you know? The ברייתא Braitah we've been working
with for the whole דף. daf. דתני, Detani, we taught in the
ברייתא Braitah we've been focused on, יצא דם שרצים שאין בהם טומאה
חמורה. yatza dam sheratzim she-ein bahem tumah chamurah. Right?
It said excluded from the פסוק pasuk of prohibition, not from the
פסוק pasuk of כרת. karet. We were focusing on the פסוק pasuk
of לעוף ולבהמה, la-oph vela-behaimah, which is the פסוק pasuk of prohibition,
and we excluded from the prohibition שרצים. sheratzim.
Okay? That they don't have a heavy טומאה. tumah. So now so
so אמר... amar... so where are we? אה, Ah, שאין בהם טומאה
חמורה. she-ein bahem tumah chamurah. So how can you say you transgress
a negative prohibition of blood of שרצים? sheratzim? It's quite explicit that
there is no prohibition of blood by שרצים. sheratzim. So אמר רבי
זירא, Amar Rabbi Zeira, you're right. There's no prohibition of blood. Here's
what he meant. התרו בו משום שרץ לוקה. Hisru bo mishum sheretz
lokei.
If you said don't eat that blood of the rodent, there's a
prohibition in the תורה Torah of eating rodents, not of eating blood,
of eating rodents, and you ate the blood, then you get מלקות
malkus because when you can't eat the meat of something, the blood
is considered like the meat. Okay? Not for the purpose of blood,
for the purpose of rodents and meat. So if they told you
don't eat that blood because you can't eat rodents, then you would
get lashes. משום דם, Mishum dam, as blood, אינו לוקה, eino lokei,
you do not get lashes. Right? And that seemed to be, you
know,
the the so therefore the point he was sort of saying was
exactly I think was now we understand was to point out this
irony. It's like you've been talking about the fact
that... because it still remains part of a שרץ. sheretz. Even if
you don't eat it with the שרץ. sheretz.
Even if you don't eat
it with the שרץ.
sheretz. It's treated like the meat of a שרץ. sheretz.
If you just sucked the blood,
you'd still eat it, right. There are general questions about when do
we consider meat to be blood to be like the meat and
so on. For example, we had before the debate of בית הלל
בית שמאי Beit Hillel Beit Shammai whether blood of a נבילה neveilah
was מטמא. metamei. Is it מטמא metamei like the meat of a
נבילה? neveilah? Okay, but we can assume for general we do consider
it to be like the meat and therefore the point of that
statement was not that it was blood but to say that it
was treated like the meat and you get שרץ. sheretz. Now we
get to the point that I had said, I jumped ahead, about
the question about how אסור, assur, how מותר mutar is the blood
of fish, grasshoppers, and humans. Let's take a look. אמר רב, Amar
Rav, דם דגים שכינסו אסור. dam dagim shekinso assur. If you actually
take the blood of fish and you gather it together, meaning it's
not just that it's in your fish and you didn't salt your
fish or it's a little bit on your plate, you actually somehow
squeezed it out and put it in a cup and you drank
it, that that would be אסור. assur. Okay, because that presumably it
might be like a מראית עין marit ayin issue, it looks like
blood, okay, but that type of thing is close enough to being
considered blood that then we would at least rabbinically forbid it.
Even if you put it
in a cup if you were at the package on the table?
Well, we're going to get to that. Okay, so anyway, so that's
what he's saying. Now, by the way, does fish blood, does it
look red?
I was just
going
to
guess that,
does it?
It does. Yeah. Okay.
Ever
catch a fish?
Yeah. Okay. All right, that's true. When you first cut it live,
you get that red, yeah, it does.
There's a lot of blood in it.
Okay, fine. So מיתיבי, meitivei, I'll ask on this. We okay, we
had just quoted a ברייתא braita which said דם דגים דם חגבים
מותר. dam dagim dam chagavim mutar.
It said blood of, okay, it said by humans it said there's
no negative prohibitions. To remind you, what did the ברייתא braita say?
It said דם האכסטים, dam ha'achastim, דם שרצים ורמשים אסור ואין חייבין
עליו. dam sheratzim u'remasim assur ve'ein chayavin alav. Okay, it says
don't eat the blood of these humans and of rodents, but you
don't transgress. Now, don't eat the blood of rodents, we understand because
now we just learned that it's considered part of a rodent, okay,
it's forbidden as a rodent. But it also said don't eat the
blood of humans. And then it which we'll get back to. And
then it said blood of fish and blood of grasshoppers is מותר.
mutar. So we're saying totally מותר. mutar. ואפילו לכתחילה. ve'afilu lechatchila.
And how you said it's אסור. assur.
So the גמרא Gemara says ההיא בשלא כינסו. hahi beshelo kinso. Well,
that's talking about that you didn't, like it maybe it ran off
on your plate, but you didn't squeeze it all out and put
it in a cup. If you actually gathered it together, it actually
would be forbidden. So the גמרא Gemara says כי קאמר רב, ki
ka'amar Rav, when did רב Rav say don't eat the blood of
fish? בשכינסו, beshekinso, you gathered it together. So the גמרא Gemara says
one minute, ודכוותיה גבי מהאכסטים בשלא כינסו. u'dechvatah gabei me'achastim beshelo kinso.
So if that's true, right, it said blood of humans is forbidden
rabbinically, blood of fish is okay. Now, when did we say blood
of fish is okay? If it is not gathered, not put all
together in a cup. Which means that blood of humans would be
forbidden even if it was not collected and put together in a
cup, just a little blood fell, you know, fell out or whatever,
it would be אסור. assur. Is that really true? ואי אסור, ve'i
assur, who says blood of humans is forbidden if it's not sort
of collected together? דתניא, detanya, we taught in the ברייתא, braita, דם
שעל גבי כיכר, dam she'al gabei kikar,
if you were let's say had bloody gums and you were eating
a bread and you had a little blood went onto the bread,
גוררו ואוכלו, gorero ve'ochlo, scrape it away and eat it. שבין השיניים
מוצצו ובולעו, shebein hashinayim motzetzo u'vole'o, but if it's still there between
your teeth in your gums, then you could just swallow it. ואינו
חושש, ve'eino choshesh, so you're not concerned.
So blood fell
on your, you have a bloody gums, you can suck it, your
gums like that if it's all in your mouth, but if as
you're eating it went out on a piece of bread, you have
to scrape it away, don't eat it. Now, isn't that a good
example? When it goes out on the bread, if it's all in
your mouth, obviously that's, maybe we're not even calling it blood at
that stage and nobody's seeing whatever, that's much more than לא כינסו.
lo kinso. But when it goes out on the bread, that would
be an example of לא כינסו, lo kinso, like a little bit
came out, you don't have it a lot collected, it's on some
piece of bread, okay, and there we do say that it is
אסור. assur. So why is the גמרא Gemara challenging? So רש"י Rashi
points out that we say in other contexts, in other גמרות Gemarot
and we're going to say later here, that that idea that there's
a little blood on the bread, scrape it away, that's only an
idea of מצוות פרוש. mitzvot prosh. It's more like, it's more like,
you know, it's not seemly to eat it, but that's not really
an איסור דרבנן. issur d'rabbanan. Okay, and the גמרא Gemara is assuming
that we know that. So we've never actually, because if it said,
if it would have had a word to say אסור, assur, what,
it's telling me advice, scrape it away? Just say אסור, assur, I'll
figure out what to do. So the fact that it says scrape
it away is telling you like, you know, you shouldn't eat, you
know, it's like it's not seemly, but it's not technically אסור. assur.
They didn't use the word אסור. assur. So how can we say
if blood of fish is מותר mutar only when it's לא כינסו,
lo kinso, blood of humans would be אסור? assur? It's not true.
Blood of humans if it's לא כינסו, lo kinso, if it's like
on the loaf of bread, it's not seemly, but it's not אסור.
assur. So let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is.
אלא כי תניא ההיא, Ela ki tanya hahi, you're right. When is
blood of fish a problem? Not just if you collected it. כי
תניא
ההיא דמותר דאית בה קשקשים. ki tanya hahi demutar de'it beh kaskasim.
Even if you collected it in a glass, if you have some,
if you have right
in the glass like the fish bones, okay. scales or whatever, thank
you, then then you can drink it even if it's in a
glass. Because then it's like as Michael said, it's like you've got
your non-dairy creamer in the, you know, in the little thing before
it became widespread, people had to require that you clearly had it
in the container, right? Or you have the container right nearby or
something like that. So that removes the מראית עין maris ayin concern,
okay, but that would be okay even if it's in a cup.
כי אמר רב אסור, Ki amar Rav assur, when did Rav say
it's forbidden? Not only is it all in a cup, but דלית
ביה קשקשין, d'leis bei kaskasin, it does not have scales. Now, what's
the comparison to humans? So let's understand this because it's an important
question by humans. So now we're saying, when did the ברייתא braisa
say that fish is okay, fish blood is okay? Fish blood is
okay either if it's just on your plate or לא כנשא lo
kinsa or even if it's in a כוס kos and you've got
your קשקשין kaskasin in it, fish blood is going to be okay.
Human blood is going to be forbidden. When will human blood be
forbidden? If it's a case where it's just לא כנשא lo kinsa
like a little bit on the on the what do you call
it, on the loaf, then it's not really forbidden, then it's just
like not seemly. Okay, but if it's gathered together in a כוס,
kos, there it really is forbidden and you don't have the היתר
heter of קשקשין. kaskasin. Why don't you have the היתר heter of
קשקשין? kaskasin? Probably because there's A, there's no way, what are you
going to do? Put like some of your human flesh from the
previous דף daf in? What are you going to do to indicate
that it's human blood, number one? And I would argue probably number
two, maybe even if there was some way to do a little
היתר, heter, human blood really looks like, you know, like animal blood
and so on, so there we're going to be much more מחמיר
machmir when it is a case of כנשא. kinsa. Interesting though, and
here's an important halachic question, where do you draw the line between
the not seemly on the bread and the totally okay if it's
between your gums? Let's say you bang your finger, whatever, you get,
you know, you have a bloody finger, are you allowed to suck
it like that? Is that a problem about like the blood on
the ככר, kikar, right, or not? Maybe still still on your body
and it obviously and clearly then it's human blood and so on.
Exactly where you draw the line is an interesting question that תוספות
Tosafos raises. I will leave you to ponder that for tomorrow.